Carlos Alas

Ph. D. Physics Candidate and M. S. Computer Science Student

Long Beach, California (661) 247-5340 calas@usc.edu

---github.com/cdalas2, ---researchgate.net/profile/Carlos-Alas, ---linkedin.com/in/carlos-alas-6a4643160/

Summary

Dedicated and versatile computational biophysicist with over 8 years of University level research and work experiences (and awards), including experimental, computational, and theoretical investigations, through which an array of soft and computational skills have been acquired for data science, including competitive team collaboration skills, machine learning, SQL, data modeling and processing, high performance parallel computing, cloud computing, writing research papers, designing research posters, and giving technical presentations to diverse audiences.

Work Experience

Travelers Insurance Company

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Data Science Leadership Development Program Intern (PI R&D - Telematics Team)

Manager: Yuriy Bakach | Project: Design a metric to evaluate night trip similarity on telematics IntelliDrive trip data

- Data pre-processing on AWS clusters through Databricks and using PySpark
- · Designed and evaluated multiple metrics and compared with business competitor's metric
- Collaborated with Traveler's business partners, telematics team, and auto team.
- 15 minute powerpoint presentation of project results
- 1st place team in Summer 2022 Case Competition (included a 15 minute team presentation of results)
- 1st place team (current standing) in Summer Intern Olympics

California Polytechnic State University San Luis Obispo

Sep 2015 - Dec 2017

Physics Department Learning Center Tutor and Grader

· Drop-in tutoring of all lower division physics courses offered, and graded homework and quizzes of undergraduate physics courses

Educational Opportunities Program (EOP) Tutor Specialist

• One-to-one tutoring of all lower division math, physics and chemistry courses offered

University of Colorado Boulder, Soft Materials Research Center

Jun 2016 - Aug 2016

Summer Research Assistant in Experimental fluid dynamics on Liquid Crystal Films

- Included a 15-minute power-point presentation and contributions to a paper submitted for peer review.
- Preprint: K. R. Ferguson, Z. Qi, A. Green, C. Alas, C. Briggs, C. S. Park, M. A. Glaser, J. E. Maclennan, N. A. Clark, Experimental studies of twodimensional laminar jet flows in freely suspended liquid crystal films, arXiv:1808.01747 [cond-mat.soft] (2018).

Antelope Valley Community College

July 2014 - Aug 2015

Learning Center Tutor and Supplemental Instructor

- Drop-in and one-to-one tutoring of all mathematics, physics, and chemistry courses offered
- Supplemental Instruction: Prepared two 1-hour weekly study sessions for students in physics.

Recent Projects

- Designed a metric to measure night trip similarity on IntelliDrive telematics data.
- · Adapted and created kinetic Monte Carlo methods to study diffusion in inhomogeneous media (studied 3 different phenomena, see GitHub)

Technical Skills

PySpark, AWS Cloud Computing, Databricks, Python, SQL/NOSQL, Machine Learning, MATLAB, C/C++, Mathematica, Designing and Evaluating Metrics, HPC, Kinetic Monte Carlo, Algorithm Design & Analysis, Data Modeling & Analysis, LaTeX

Publications

Education

University of Southern California

Aug 2018 - Present

Ph. D in Physics (5-year program), 3.4 GPA

· Courses Passed: Thermodynamics & Statistical Physics, Quantum Mech., Methods of Theoretical Physics, Advanced Mech., Advanced E&M

M. S. in Computer Science (High Performance Computing and Simulations), 3.7 GPA

- · Courses Passed: Database Systems, Analysis of Algorithms, Scient. Computing & Visualization, Methods of Comp. Physics, Numerical Analysis
- · Courses Planned: Machine Learning, Information Retrieval & Web Search Engines, High Performance Computing and Simulation

Research Assistant in Theoretical & Computational Membrane and Protein Biophysics, PI: Christoph Haselwandter

- Currently researching: Stochastic lattice model and simulations of nuclear membrane emerin nanodomains, 2022-2023
- Currently researching: Dependence of protein-induced lipid bilayer Midplane deformations on protein shape, 2021-2023
- Polishing manuscript for submission this Fall: Thermosensing via protein-bilayer interactions, 2021-2022
- Submitting manuscript this Summer: Dependence of protein-induced lipid bilayer thickness deformations on protein shape, 2019-2021
- Research presentations and posters: APS March Meeting 2022, USC QCB Symposium 2022, Dynamolinc Annual Meeting 2022
- · Collaborations with international experimental groups (USC Pinaud Lab and CNRS in France)

Teaching Assistant in Physics

- · Head TA: Taught and trained graduate students on teaching and grading physics lab sections
- · Wrote solutions for and graded lecture section exams, Drop-in tutoring for all undergraduate physics courses offered

California Polytechnics State University San Luis Obispo

Sep 2015 - Dec 2017

Bachelors of Science in Physics, Minor in Math, 3.4 Cumulative GPA, 3.7 Major GPA

Research Assistant in Theoretical & Computational Fluid and Bacteria Dynamics, Pl: Dr. Tatiana Kuriabova

- Work published in Journal of Fluid Mechanics
- Included research presentations and poster board sessions (Frost Summer Research Conference 2016, COSAM Spring 2018)

Student/Faculty Research in Active Matter Experiments on Liquid Crystal Films, PI: Dr. Jon Fernsler

Student/Faculty Research in Electromagnetic Drive Propulsion Experiments, PI: Dr. Robert Echols

Antelope Valley Community College

Sep 2008 - Jun 2015

Associate in Science in LAS: Math and Sciences, cum laude

Associate in Science in Physics-Transfer, cum laude

Student/Faculty Research in High Speed Camera Capture of Strike Kinematics of Hadrurus Arizonensis Scorpion Experiments, Pl: Dr. Zia Nisani

Fellowships, Scholarships, and Awards

Diversity, Inclusion, and Access Initiative Fellowship (Aug 2018), Frost Summer Research Scholarship (Jun 2017), SMRC REU Scholarship (Jun 2016), Helen SanderCock Foundation Scholarship (May 2016), Flight Test Historical Foundation Scholarship (May 2015), Subject Area Award in Physics awarded at Antelope Valley College's Honors Convocation (Nominating Instructors: Dr. Jason Bowen, Dr. Alexandra Schroer, May 2015)

Volunteer Experiences

Antelope Valley College

- Cal Tech Science Olympiad Competition Event Designer &/or Supervisor (STEM Program Director: Christos Valiotis), every February 2015-2019
- Physics experiments demonstration at Barnes and Noble of Palmdale, CA (STEM Outreach Coordinator: Jamie Jones), June 14, 2018

California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo

• Physics experiments demonstrations at Baywood Elementary School of Los Osos, CA (Event Director: Dr. Karl Saunders), January 27, 2018

References

Available upon request